let set3=
[
    {
        question:`1. Match List I to List II and select the correct answer with
        the code given below:
        List-I (Name of acids/bases) List-II (found in)
        A. Formic acid 1.Ant’s Sting
        B. Calcium hydroxide 2.Lime water
        C. Tartaric acid 3.Soap
        D. Sodium hydroxide 4.Tamarind and grape fruit
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 2 3 4',
'B. 1 2 4 3',
'C. 4 3 1 2',
'D. 4 2 1 3',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: These substances taste sour because they contain
        acids, whereas the substances which are bitter in taste and feel
        soapy on touch are known as bases. The names of some major acids
        and related substances are:
        Name of acid Found in
        1. Acetic acid Vinegar
        2. Formic acid Ant’s sting
        3. Citric acid Citrus fruits such as oranges, lemons,
        etc.
        4. Lactic acid Curd
        5. Oxalic acid Spinach
        6. Ascorbic acid Amla, Citrus fruits (Vitamin C)
        7. Tartaric acid Tamarind, grapes, unripe mangoes, etc.
        All the acids mentioned above occur in nature.
        Name of base Found in
        1. Calcium hydroxide : Lime water
        2. Ammonium hydroxide : Window cleaner
        3. Sodium hydroxide/Potassium hydroxid: Soap
        4. Magnesium hydroxide: Milk of magnesia
        `
    },
    {
        question:`2. Consider the following assertions:
        1. The solutions which do not change the colour of either red or blue
        litmus are known as neutral solutions.
        2. Turmeric, litmus, china rose petals are some of the naturally
        occurring indicators.
        3. When acid content is high in rain water, then it is called acid rain.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 2 and 3 only',
'C. 3 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation: Neutral solution is a solution whose pH is close to 7.
        They prefer remaining at a perfect balance.Usually a neutral solution
        is neither acidic nor basic. It doesn't imply that the neutral solution
        lack charged ions.
        Natural Indicator is a type of indicator that can be found naturally
        and can determine whether the substance is an acidic substance or a
        basic substance. Some examples of natural indicators are red
        cabbage, turmeric, grape juice, turnip skin, curry powder, cherries,
        beetroots, onion, tomato, etc.
        Acid rain, or acid deposition, is a broad term that includes any form
        of precipitation with acidic components, such as sulfuric or nitric
        acid that fall to the ground from the atmosphere in wet or dry
        forms. This can include rain, snow, fog, hail or even dust that is
        acidic.
        Acid rain results when sulfur dioxide (SO2) and nitrogen oxides
        (NOX) are emitted into the atmosphere and transported by wind and
        air currents. The SO2 and NOX react with water, oxygen and other
        chemicals to form sulfuric and nitric acids. These then mix with
        water and other materials before falling to the ground.
        While a small portion of the SO2 and NOX that cause acid rain is
        from natural sources such as volcanoes, most of it comes from the
        burning of fossil fuels. The major sources of SO2 and NOX in the
        atmosphere are:
        1. Burning of fossil fuels to generate electricity. Two thirds of
        SO2 and one fourth of NOX in the atmosphere come from electric
        power generators.
        2. Vehicles and heavy equipment.
        3. Manufacturing, oil refineries and other industries.
        Winds can blow SO2 and NOX over long distances and across borders
        making acid rain a problem for everyone and not just those who live
        close to these sources.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`3. Which of the following assertions is/are correct with
        reference to soil treatment due to excessive use of chemical
        fertilisers?
        1. Excessive use of chemical fertilisers makes the soil acidic.
        2. If the soil is acidic, organic matter is added to it.
        Use the code given below to select the correct answer :
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: Excessive use of chemical fertilisers makes the soil
        acidic. Plants do not grow well when the soil is either too acidic or
        too basic. When the soil is too acidic, it is treated with bases like
        quicklime (calcium oxide) or slaked lime (calcium hydroxide). If the
        soil is basic, organic matter (compost) is added to it. Organic matter
        releases acids which neutralises the basic nature of the soil.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`4. Regarding the examples of neutralisation in Everyday Life,
        consider the following assertions :
        1. The waste of many factories contain acids; therefore, they are
        neutralised by adding basic substances before they are allowed to
        flow into the water bodies.
        2. Magnesium hydroxide neutralises the effect of excessive acid in
        the stomach.
        3. The effect of the acid injected into the skin through an ant bite
        can be neutralised by rubbing moist baking soda (sodium hydrogen
        carbonate) or calamine solution.
        Which of the above assertions is /are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. 3 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation: The wastes of many factories contain acids. If they
        are allowed to flow into the water bodies, the acids will kill fish and
        other organisms. The factory wastes are, therefore, neutralised by
        adding basic substances.
        Our stomach contains hydrochloric acid. It helps us to digest food.
        But too much of acid in the stomach causes indigestion, which is
        painful. To relieve indigestion, we take an antacid such as milk of
        magnesia, which contains magnesium hydroxide. It neutralises the
        effect of excessive acid.
        When an ant bites, it injects the acidic liquid (formic acid) into the
        skin. The effect of the acid can be neutralised by rubbing moist
        baking soda (sodium hydrogencarbonate) or calamine solution, which
        contains zinc carbonate.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`5. Which of the following examples is/are related to physical
        change?
        1. Tearing of paper
        2. Change in color
        3. Combining of Hydrogen and Oxygen to form water
        4. Burning of paper
        Use the code given below to select the correct answer :
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 1 and 2 only',
'C. 2 and 3 only',
'D. 1, 2, 3 and 4'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: In tearing of paper, it had underwent changes in size.
        Properties such as shape,size,colour,state of a substance are called
        physical properties. A change in which a substance undergoes a
        change in its physical properties is called a physical change.
        Rest, other changes are the examples of chemical change.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`6. In terms of physical and chemical changes, which of the
        following assertions is/are correct?
        1. All physical changes are irreversible, while chemical changes are
        reversible.
        2. The following may accompany a chemical change:-Sound may be
        produced, Heat, light or any other radiation (ultraviolet, for
        example) may be given or absorbed.
        Use the code given below to select the correct answer :
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation:
        Physical changes: Changes in the Physical Properties of a Substance
        are known as Physical Changes. Physical Properties of a Substance
        include colour, size, shape, state, temperature, odour, appearance,
        texture and many more. In addition, Physical Changes do not lead to
        the formation of new substances. Physical Changes may or may not
        be reversible.
        Examples of Physical Change
         Breaking/Crushing of any Object
         Expansion of Metal on Heating
         Dissolving Sugar or Salt (Solute) in Water (Solvent) (as a
        result, a solution is formed)
         Solidification of Molten Metal on Cooling
         Shredding Paper
        Chemical Changes: One or more substances, at times, react with one
        another or substances which are readily available in the environment.
        This consequently leads to the formation of a new substance(s). The
        formation of the new substance can also be accompanied by one or
        more of the following:
        1. Emission of Heat (Exothermic Reaction) as a result of a Chemical
        Changes
        2. Absorption of Heat (Endothermic Reaction) as a result of a
        Chemical Changes
        3. Emission Light as a result of a Chemical Changes
        4. Production of Sound as a result of a Chemical Changes
        5. Change or emission of Odour as a result of a Chemical Changes
        6. Emission of Gas as a result of a Chemical Changes
        `
    },
    {
        question:`7. Which of the following is not a physical change?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. Boiling of water to give water vapour',
'B. Melting of ice to give water',
'C. Dissolution of salt in water',
'D. Combustion of Liquefied Petroleum Gas (LPG)'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation: A physical change involves only change in physical state
        whereas a chemical change results the formation of new substances.
        Boiling of water, melting of ice and dissolution of salt are physical
        changes as no new products are formed.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`8. Which of the following are exothermic processes?
        1. Reaction of water with quick lime
        2. Dilution of an acid
        3. Evaporation of water
        4. Sublimation of camphor (crystals)
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2',
'B. 2 and 3',
'C. 1 and 4',
'D. 3 and 4'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: Exothermic reactions are reactions or processes that
        release energy, usually in the form of heat or light. In an exothermic
        reaction, energy is released because the total energy of the
        products is less than the total energy of the reactants. For this
        reason, the change in enthalpy, [latex]\Delta H[/latex], for an
        exothermic reaction will always be negative. In the presence of
        water, a strong acid will dissociate quickly and release heat, so it is
        an exothermic reaction.
        Endothermic reactions are reactions that require external energy,
        usually in the form of heat, for the reaction to proceed. Since
        endothermic reactions draw in heat from their surroundings, they
        tend to cause their environments to cool down. They are also
        generally non-spontaneous, since endothermic reactions yield
        products that are higher in energy than the reactants. As such, the
        change in enthalpy for an endothermic reaction is always positive. In
        order to melt the ice cube, heat is required, so the process is
        endothermic.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`9. The process used to prevent rusting of iron, in which a thin
        coat of zinc is provided over iron surface. This process is:
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. Galvanization',
'B. Electroplating',
'C. Painting in zinc',
'D. None of these'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: Galvanizing, protection of iron or steel against
        exposure to the atmosphere and consequent rusting by application of
        a zinc coating. Properly applied, galvanizing may protect from
        atmospheric corrosion for 15 to 30 years or more. As discontinuities
        or porosity develop in the coating, galvanic or electrolytic action
        ensues; the iron or steel, however, is protected by sacrificial
        corrosion, a phenomenon in which, as long as the zinc and the iron are
        in contact, atmospheric oxidation spares the iron and affects the
        zinc.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`10. Which statement is correct regarding acids?
        1. Acid is a molecule which donate proton or accept electron pair in
        reactions.
        2. Acid increases the concentration of hydrogen atoms or hydronium
        atoms in water.
        3. Acids have pH value less than 7.
        4. Acid in the stomach helps in the digestion of food.
        Use correct statements:
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. Only 1',
'B. Both 2 and 4',
'C. Both 3 and 4',
'D. All the above'
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation: Acid, any substance that in water solution tastes sour,
        changes the colour of certain indicators (e.g., reddens
        blue litmus paper), reacts with some metals (e.g., iron)
        toliberate hydrogen, reacts with bases to form salts, and promotes
        certain chemical reactions (acid catalysis). Examples of acids include
        the inorganic substances known as the mineral acids—sulfuric, nitric,
        hydrochloric, and phosphoric acids—and the
        organic compounds belonging to the carboxylic acid, sulfonic acid,
        and phenol groups.
        Acids may be identified as either strong or weak acids based on how
        completely they dissociate into their ions in water. A strong acid,
        such as hydrochloric acid, completely dissociates into its ions in
        water. A weak acid only partly dissociates into its ions, so the
        solution contains water, ions, and the acid (e.g., acetic acid).
        `
    }
]